What was the most difficult job you ever did?
ما أصعب عمل قمت به على الإطلاق؟
Was it working in the sun?
هل كان العمل تحت الشمس؟
Was it working to provide food for a family or a community?
أم تأمين الطعام لأسرة أو مجموعة من الأفراد؟
Was it working days and nights trying to protect lives and property?
هل كان العمل لأيام وليال لحماية الأرواح والممتلكات؟
Was it working alone
هل كان العمل وحيداً؟
or working on a project that wasn't guaranteed to succeed,
أم كان العمل على مشروع غير مضمون النجاح،
but that might improve human health or save a life?
لكنه قد يحسن صحة الإنسان أو ينقذ حياته؟
Was it working to build something, create something, make a work of art?
هل كان العمل لبناء أو ابتكار شيء أو صنع تحفة فنية؟
Was it work for which you were never sure
هل كان قيامك بعمل غير متأكد
The people in our communities who do these jobs
الناس الذين يقومون بهذه الأعمال في مجتمعاتنا
deserve our attention, our love and our deepest support.
يستحقون أن يحظوا بانتباهنا وحبنا ودعمنا الكبير.
But people aren't the only ones in our communities
لكن البشر في مجتمعاتنا ليسوا وحدهم
who do these difficult jobs.
من يقوم بهذه المهام الصعبة،
These jobs are also done by the plants, the animals
بل تقوم بها النباتات والحيوانات أيضًا
and the ecosystems on our planet,
والنظم البيئية على كوكبنا.
including the ecosystems I study: the tropical coral reefs.
ومن ضمن الأنظمة البيئية التي أدرسها: الشعاب المرجانية الاستوائية.
They provide food, income and food security
تؤمن الغذاء والدخل الاقتصادي والأمن الغذائي
for hundreds of millions of people around the world.
لمئات الملايين من الأشخاص حول العالم.
Coral reefs are security guards.
الشعاب المرجانية كالحرس،
The structures that they build protect our shorelines
فالهياكل التي تشكلها تحمي شواطئنا
from storm surge and waves,
من الأمواج العاتية أثناء العواصف،
and the biological systems that they house filter the water
كما أنها تحتوي على نظم حيوية تعمل على تنقية المياه
and make it safer for us to work and play.
وجعلها أكثر أماناً لنا أثناء العمل واللعب.
Coral reefs are chemists.
الشعاب المرجانية كالكيميائيين،
The molecules that we're discovering on coral reefs are increasingly important
فالجزيئات المكتشفَة على الشعاب المرجانية بالغة الأهمية
in the search for new antibiotics and new cancer drugs.
في البحث عن المضادات الحيوية وأدوية جديدة للسرطان.
And coral reefs are artists.
إن الشعاب المرجانية كالفنانين،
The structures that they build
فالهياكل التي تشكلها
are some of the most beautiful things on planet Earth.
من أجمل الأشياء على وجه الأرض،
And this beauty is the foundation of the tourism industry
وهذا الجمال هو أساس الجذب السياحي
in many countries with few or little other natural resources.
في العديد من الدول التي تحتوي على القليل من الموارد الطبيعية الأخرى.
So for all of these reasons, all of these ecosystem services,
إذًا، نظرًا لكل هذه الأسباب، وللخدمات التي تقدمها هذه النظم البيئية،
economists estimate the value of the world's coral reefs
يقدر علماء الاقتصاد أن قيمة الشعاب المرجانية في العالم
in the hundreds of billions of dollars per year.
تساوي مئات مليارات الدولارات سنويًا،
And yet despite all that hard work being done for us
ورغم كل العمل الشاق الذي تقوم به من أجلنا
and all that wealth that we gain,
وكل الثروة التي نكسبها منها،
we have done almost everything we possibly could to destroy that.
إلا أننا لم نوفر جهدًا في تدميرها.
We have taken the fish out of the oceans
فقد استنزفنا الأسماك من المحيطات،
and we have added in fertilizer, sewage,
ورميناها بالأسمدة والصرف الصحي
diseases, oil, pollution, sediments.
والأمراض والمشتقات النفطية والملوثات والمخلفات.
We have trampled the reefs physically with our boats, our fins, our bulldozers,
سحقنا هذه الشعاب بمراكبنا وجرافاتنا،
and we have changed the chemistry of the entire sea,
وغيرنا كيمياء البحر بأكمله،
warmed the waters and made storms worse.
وتسببنا بزيادة دفء الماء واشتداد العواصف،
And these would all be bad on their own,
ورغم أن كل ما سبق كارثة بحد ذاته
but these threats magnify each other
إلا أن هذه التهديدات تضخم بعضها البعض،
and compound one another and make each other worse.
ويضيف بعضها إلى بعض لتزيد كل واحدة منها الأخرى سوءًا.
I'll give you an example.
سأعطيكم مثالًا.
Where I live and work, in Curaçao, a tropical storm went by a few years ago.
حيث كنت أعيش وأعمل في (كوراساو) حدثت عاصفة استوائية منذ بضع سنوات،
And on the eastern end of the island,
وعلى الطرف الشرقي للجزيرة،
where the reefs are intact and thriving,
حيث الشعاب المرجانية سليمة ومزدهرة،
you could barely tell a tropical storm had passed.
بالكاد يمكنك أن تتصور أن عاصفة استوائية مرت من هناك،
But in town, where corals had died from overfishing, from pollution,
لكن في البلدة، حيث ماتت الشعاب نتيجة صيد الأسماك الجائر والتلوث،
the tropical storm picked up the dead corals
انجرفت الشعاب الميتة مع العاصفة،
and used them as bludgeons to kill the corals that were left.
وأصبحت كالهراوات تدمر ما تبقى من الشعاب.
This is a coral that I studied during my PhD --
هذه الشعاب التي درستها وأنا أحضر لنيل الدكتوراه،
I got to know it quite well.
تعرفت عليها جيدًا،
And after this storm took off half of its tissue,
وبعدما اقتلعت العاصفة حوالي نصف نسيجها،
it became infested with algae,
صارت مليئة بالطحالب،
the algae overgrew the tissue and that coral died.
وفاقت هذه الطحالب النسيج المرجاني مما أدى لموته.
This magnification of threats, this compounding of factors
إن اجتماع عوامل التهديد معًا
is what Jeremy Jackson describes as the "slippery slope to slime."
هو ما وصفه (جيريمي جاكسون) بأنه "الانحدار المنزلق نحو الوحل".
It's hardly even a metaphor because many of our reefs now
وهذا بالكاد تعبير مجازي لأن العديد من الشعاب الآن
are literally bacteria and algae and slime.
صارت جراثيمًا وطحالبًا ووحلًا.
Now, this is the part of the talk
والآن تتوقعون مني
where you may expect me to launch into my plea
أن أناشدكم جميعًا
for us to all save the coral reefs.
لإنقاذ الشعاب المرجانية.
But I have a confession to make:
لكن لدي اعتراف:
that phrase drives me nuts.
تلك العبارة تقودني إلى الجنون،
Whether I see it in a tweet, in a news headline
سواءً رأيتها في تغريدة أو في إحدى عناوين الأخبار
or the glossy pages of a conservation brochure,
أو صفحة في إحدى كتيبات المحافظة على البيئة،
that phrase bothers me,
تلك العبارة تزعجني،
because we as conservationists have been sounding the alarms
لأننا نحن المحافظون أطلقنا إنذارًا
And yet, almost everyone I meet, no matter how educated,
ورغم ذلك، فكل شخص ألقاه تقريبًا، وأيًا كان مستوى تعليمه،
is not sure what a coral is or where they come from.
لا يعرف ما هو المرجان ولا من أين يأتي.
How would we get someone to care about the world's coral reefs
كيف يمكن أن نجعل أحدهم يهتم بالشعاب المرجانية حول العالم
when it's an abstract thing they can barely understand?
وهي شيء مجرد بالكاد يستطيع فهمه؟
If they don't understand what a coral is or where it comes from,
إن لم يفهموا ماهية المرجان أو من أين يأتي،
or how funny or interesting or beautiful it is,
أو كم هو ظريف ومشوق وجميل
why would we expect them to care about saving them?
فكيف نتوقع أن يهتموا بإنقاذه؟
So let's change that.
إذًا، لنغير ذلك.
What is a coral and where does it come from?
ما هو المرجان وكيف يتشكل؟
Corals are born in a number of different ways,
يولد المرجان بعدة طرق،
but most often by mass spawning: all of the individuals of a single species
لكن الشائع هو التكاثر الجماعي: فكل أفراد النوع الواحد
on one night a year,
في ليلة واحدة في العام،
releasing all the eggs they've made that year
تضع جميع البيض الذي كونته خلال العام
into the water column,
في صف مائي،
packaged into bundles with sperm cells.
وتجمعه في حزم مع خلايا نطفية.
And those bundles go to the surface of the ocean and break apart.
وتصعد هذه الحزم إلى سطح المحيط ثم تنشق إلى أجزاء.
And hopefully -- hopefully -- at the surface of the ocean,
على أمل، أنه على سطح المحيط
they meet the eggs and sperm from other corals.
سيلتقي البيض مع نطف مرجان آخر.
And that is why you need lots of corals on a coral reef --
لذا نحتاج الكثير من المرجان في الشعاب المرجانية،
so that all of their eggs can meet their match at the surface.
ليلتقي البيض مع قرائنه عند السطح.
When they're fertilized, they do what any other animal egg does:
وعندما تُخصَّب، تتصرف كبيض أي حيوان آخر:
divides in half again and again and again.
تنقسم إلى نصفين، مرة واثنتين وهكذا.
Taking these photos under the microscope every year
إن التقاط مثل هذه الصور تحت المجهر سنويًا
is one of my favorite and most magical moments of the year.
أحد أعمالي المفضلة، وأكثر الأوقات سحراً خلال العام.
At the end of all this cell division, they turn into a swimming larva --
في نهاية هذا الانقسام الخلوي، تتحول إلى يرقة عائمة،
a little tiny blob of fat the size of a poppy seed,
كتلة صغيرة دهنية بحجم بذرة الخشخاش،
but with all of the sensory systems that we have.
لكن مع نظام الحواس الكامل الذي نملكه.
They can sense color and light, textures, chemicals, pH.
يمكنها الشعور باللون والضوء والتراكيب والمواد الكيميائية ودرجة الحموضة،
They can even feel pressure waves; they can hear sound.
يمكنها حتى الشعور بضغط الأمواج، ويمكنها سماع الأصوات.
And they use those talents
وتستعمل تلك القدرات
to search the bottom of the reef for a place to attach
لتبحث عن مكان تتشبّث به في قاع الشعاب
and live the rest of their lives.
وتعيش بقية حياتها.
So imagine finding a place where you would live the rest of your life
تصور أن يقع على عاتقك إيجاد مكان تمضي فيه بقية عمرك
when you were just two days old.
بينما عمرك لا يتجاوز اليومين.
They attach in the place they find most suitable,
تتشبث في المكان الأنسب لها،
they build a skeleton underneath themselves,
تكوّن هيكلًا عظميًا أسفلها،
they build a mouth and tentacles,
تكوّن فمًا ومجسات،
and then they begin the difficult work of building the world's coral reefs.
وتبدأ عملها الشاق بتكوين الشعاب المرجانية في العالم.
One coral polyp will divide itself again and again and again,
إن سليلة مرجانية واحدة ستنقسم مرة واثنتين وهكذا،
leaving a limestone skeleton underneath itself
تاركةً هيكلًا كلسيًا أسفلها
and growing up toward the sun.
لتنمو باتجاه الشمس.
Given hundreds of years and many species,
مع مرور السنين وبوجود العديد من الأنواع،
what you get is a massive limestone structure
ما تحصل عليه هو كتلة ضخمة كلسية
that can be seen from space in many cases,
يمكن رؤيتها من الفضاء في عدة مناسبات،
covered by a thin skin of these hardworking animals.
تغطيها طبقة رقيقة من هذه الحيوانات المجتهدة.
Now, there are only a few hundred species of corals on the planet, maybe 1,000.
حاليا لا يوجد سوى عدة مئات من الأنواع المرجانية وربما لا تتجاوز 1000
But these systems house millions and millions of other species,
لكنها تأوي ملايين الملايين من الأنواع الأخرى،
and that diversity is what stabilizes the systems,
وهذا التنوع هو ما يسبب استقرارها،
and it's where we're finding our new medicines.
وهو المكان الذي نكتشف فيه أدويتنا الجديدة
I'm lucky enough to work on the island of Curaçao,
إنني محظوظة بالعمل على جزيرة (كوراساو)،
where we still have reefs that look like this.
حيث ما زلنا نملك شعابًا تبدو بهذا الشكل.
But, indeed, much of the Caribbean and much of our world
لكن في الحقيقة، الكثير من مناطق الكاريبي والكثير من عالمنا
is much more like this.
أشبه بهذا.
Scientists have studied in increasing detail
درس العلماء بالتفصيل
the loss of the world's coral reefs,
خسارة العالم للشعاب المرجانية،
and they have documented with increasing certainty the causes.
ووثقوا الأسباب بشكل شبه مؤكد.
But in my research, I'm not interested in looking backward.
لكن في أبحاثي، لست مهتمة بالنظر للخلف.
My colleagues and I in Curaçao are interested in looking forward
أنا وزملائي في (كوراساو) مهتمون بالنظر للأمام
at what might be.
وما قد يكون.
And we have the tiniest reason to be optimistic.
ولدينا أصغر الأسباب لنتفاءل.
Because even in some of these reefs
إذ انه حتى في بعض هذه الشعاب،
that we probably could have written off long ago,
والتي كان من الممكن أن تزول منذ زمن،
we sometimes see baby corals arrive and survive anyway.
ما زلنا في بعض الأحيان نشهد ظهور صغار المرجان ونجاتها على أي حال.
And we're starting to think that baby corals may have the ability
وبدأنا نفكر أن صغار المرجان قد يكون ليها القدرة
to adjust to some of the conditions that the adults couldn't.
على التكيّف مع بعض هذه الظروف على عكس البالغ منها.
They may be able to adjust
ربما هي قادرة على التكيّف
So in the research I do with my colleagues in Curaçao,
لذا في بحثي مع زملائي في (كوراساو)
we try to figure out what a baby coral needs
نحاول أن نحدد احتياجات صغار المرجان
in that critical early stage,
في تلك المرحلة المبكرة الحرجة،
what it's looking for
ما الذي تبحث عنه
and how we can try to help it through that process.
وكيف يمكننا مساعدتها خلال تلك العملية.
I'm going to show you three examples of the work we've done
سأعرض عليكم ثلاثة أمثلة للعمل الذي نقوم به
to try to answer those questions.
للإجابة عن هذه الأسئلة.
A few years ago we took a 3D printer and we made coral choice surveys --
منذ عدة سنوات أخذنا طابعة ثلاثية الأبعاد وقمنا بتجربة اختيار المرجان
different colors and different textures,
بألوان وأنسجة مختلفة
and we simply asked the coral where they preferred to settle.
وسألنا المرجان ببساطة أين يريد أن يستقر.
And we found that corals, even without the biology involved,
وجدنا أن المرجان، وبدون تدخل بيولوجي،
still prefer white and pink, the colors of a healthy reef.
ما زال يفضل اللونين الأبيض والزهري: ألوان الشعاب المرجانية السليمة
And they prefer crevices and grooves and holes,
و يفضل الشقوق والأخاديد والحفر
where they will be safe from being trampled
حيث يكون بمأمن من أن يتم دهسه
or eaten by a predator.
أو أكله من كائن مفترس.
So we can use this knowledge,
لذا يمكن استخدام هذه المعلومة
we can go back and say we need to restore those factors --
يمكننا أن نعود ونقول أننا في حاجة لاستعادة هذه العوامل
that pink, that white, those crevices, those hard surfaces --
الزهري والأبيض والشقوق والأسطح القاسية
in our conservation projects.
في مشروعنا لحفظ البيئة.
We can also use that knowledge
كما يمكن استخدام هذه المعلومة
if we're going to put something underwater, like a sea wall or a pier.
في حالة وضع شيء تحت الماء كجدار أو رصيف بحري.
We can choose to use the materials and colors and textures
يمكن أن نختار استخدام هذه المواد والألوان والأنسجة
that might bias the system back toward those corals.
بما قد يجعل المنظومة تعود لتنحاز إلى شعاب المرجان.
Now in addition to the surfaces,
الآن، وبالإضافة لدراسة الأسطح
we also study the chemical and microbial signals
يمكننا دراسة الإشارات الكيميائية والميكروبية
that attract corals to reefs.
التي تجذب المرجان إلى الشعاب.
Starting about six years ago, I began culturing bacteria
بدأتُ منذ حوالي ستة أعوام بتحضير مزارع جرثومية
from surfaces where corals had settled.
من السطوح التي استقر عليها المرجان،
And I tried those one by one by one,
ودرستها الواحدة تلو الأخرى
looking for the bacteria that would convince corals to settle and attach.
باحثةً عن الجراثيم التي تقنع المرجان بالاستقرار والتثبت.
And we now have many bacterial strains in our freezer
ولدينا حاليًا في مجمداتنا سلالات جرثومية عديدة
that will reliably cause corals
تتسبب، بشكل موثوق،
to go through that settlement and attachment process.
باستقرار وتثبت المرجان.
So as we speak,
وبينما نتحدث الآن
my colleagues in Curaçao are testing those bacteria
يختبر زملائي في (كوراساو) هذه الجراثيم
to see if they'll help us raise more coral settlers in the lab,
ليبحثوا إمكانية مساهمتها في زيادة مستوطنات للشعاب في المختبر،
and to see if those coral settlers will survive better
وليروا إن كانت ستبقى هذه المستوطنات على قيد الحياة
when we put them back underwater.
عندما نعيدها إلى الماء.
Now in addition to these tools, we also try to uncover the mysteries
فضلًا عن هذه الأدوات نعمل حاليًا على كشف أسرار
of species that are under-studied.
الأنواع قيد الدراسة.
This is one of my favorite corals, and always has been:
هذه إحدى أنواع المرجان المفضلة لدي:
dendrogyra cylindrus, the pillar coral.
(ديندروغيرا سايلندروس) المرجان العموي.
I love it because it makes this ridiculous shape,
أحبه لأنه يكوّن هذا الشكل الغريب،
because its tentacles are fat and look fuzzy
وبسبب لوامسه الدهنية المغطاة بالزغب
and because it's rare.
ولأنه نادر.
Finding one of these on a reef is a treat.
من المبهج أن تجد واحداً كهذا ضمن الشعاب المرجانية.
In fact, it's so rare,
في الحقيقة، هو نادر
that last year it was listed as a threatened species
لدرجة أنه صُنّف العام الماضي كنوع مهدد
on the endangered species list.
ضمن قائمة الأنواع المهددة بالانقراض.
And this was in part because in over 30 years of research surveys,
وذلك جزئيًا بسبب أن الإحصاءات على مدى ال30 سنة الماضية
scientists had never found a baby pillar coral.
لم تجد أية صغار للمرجان العمودي.
We weren't even sure if they could still reproduce,
حتى أننا لم نكن واثقين إن ما زال بإمكانها أن تتكاثر
or if they were still reproducing.
أو أنها ما زالت تتكاثر.
So four years ago, we started following these at night
بدأنا منذ أربع سنوات بمتابعة هذه ليلًا
and watching to see if we could figure out when they spawn in Curaçao.
ومراقبتها لنرى إذا كانت ستتكاثر في (كوراساو).
We got some good tips from our colleagues in Florida,
حصلنا على بعض النصائح الجيدة من زملائنا في فلوريدا
who had seen one in 2007, one in 2008,
الذين رأوا إحداها في 2007 وآخر في 2008
and eventually we figured out when they spawn in Curaçao
وفي النهاية اكتشفنا متى تتكاثر في (كوراساو)
and we caught it.
وأمسكنا بها.
Here's a female on the left with some eggs in her tissue,
هذه أنثى على اليسار مع بعض البيض فس نسيجها،
about to release them into the seawater.
وهي على وشك اطلاقه في مياه البحر.
And here's a male on the right, releasing sperm.
وهذا ذكر على اليمين يطلق النطاف.
We collected this, we got it back to the lab, we got it to fertilize
جمعنا هذه وأعدنا إلى المخبر وقمنا بتخصيبها
and we got baby pillar corals swimming in our lab.
وأخيرًا بدأ صغير المرجان العمودي يسبح في مختبرنا.
Thanks to the work of our scientific aunts and uncles,
شكراً لعمل "أقربائي في العلم"،
and thanks to the 10 years of practice we've had in Curaçao
وشكراً لعشر سنوات من التدريب في (كوراساو)
at raising other coral species,
لتربية أنواع أخرى من المرجان،
we got some of those larvae to go through the rest of the process
حصلنا على بعض هذه اليرقات لاستكمال العمل
and settle and attach,
على الاستقرار والتثبت،
and turn into metamorphosed corals.
والعودة إلى المرجان المجازي.
So this is the first pillar coral baby that anyone ever saw.
إذًا، هذا كان أول مرجان عمودي صغير يُرى على الإطلاق.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And I have to say -- if you think baby pandas are cute,
وعلي أن أقول لكم إذا كنتم تعتقدون أن صغار الباندا ظريفة،
this is cuter.
فهذه أظرف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we're starting to figure out the secrets to this process,
ونحن في طور اكتشاف أسرار هذه العملية
the secrets of coral reproduction and how we might help them.
وأسرار تكاثر الشعاب المرجانية وكيف يمكن مساعدتها.
And this is true all around the world;
وهذا ما يحدث في جميع أنحاء العالم؛
scientists are figuring out new ways to handle their embryos,
يعمل العلماء على اكتشاف طرق جديدة للعناية بأجنتها،
to get them to settle,
لجعلها تستقر،
maybe even figuring out the methods to preserve them at low temperatures,
وربما إيجاد طرق لحفظها في درجة حرارة منخفضة
so that we can preserve their genetic diversity
بحيث نتمكن من حفظ تنوعها الوراثي
and work with them more often.
والعمل عليها بشكل أكبر.
But this is still so low-tech.
لكن ما زلنا نعمل بتقنية محدودة
We are limited by the space on our bench, the number of hands in the lab
يحدنا مكان العمل وعدد الأيدي العاملة في المختبر
and the number of coffees we can drink in any given hour.
وعدد فناجين القهوة التي يمكن أن نحتسيها كل ساعة.
Now, compare that to our other crises
الآن وبالمقارنة مع مصائبنا الأخرى
and our other areas of concern as a society.
والنواحي الأخرى المهمة في مجتمعنا
We have advanced medical technology, we have defense technology,
نملك تقنية طبية متقدمة وتقنية دفاعية
we have scientific technology,
وتقنية علمية
we even have advanced technology for art.
حتى أن لدينا تقنية حديثة للفنون
But our technology for conservation is behind.
غير أن تقنيتنا في حماية مواردنا ما زالت متأخرة.
Think back to the most difficult job you ever did.
تذكر أصعب مهنة قمت بها على الإطلاق.
Many of you would say it was being a parent.
قد يقول أكثركم أن تكون أبًا أو أمًا.
My mother described being a parent
أمي كانت تقول عن ذلك
as something that makes your life far more amazing and far more difficult
بأنه شيء يجعل حياتك أصعب وأبدع
than you could've ever possibly imagined.
أكثر مما قد تتصور.
I've been trying to help corals become parents for over 10 years now.
أحاول مساعدة الشعاب المرجانية لتكون آباءً منذ أكثر من 10 سنوات.
And watching the wonder of life
وشهود معجزة الحياة
has certainly filled me with amazement to the core of my soul.
مما يملأني حتمًا بالدهشة حتى أعماق روحي.
But I've also seen how difficult it is for them to become parents.
لكنني شاهدت أيضًا كم هو صعب عليهم أن يكونوا آباء.
The pillar corals spawned again two weeks ago,
تكاثر المرجان العمودي مرة أخرى منذ أسبوعين،
and we collected their eggs and brought them back to the lab.
جمعنا البيض وعدنا به إلى المختبر،
And here you see one embryo dividing,
وهنا يمكنك أن ترى جنينًا ينقسم،
alongside 14 eggs that didn't fertilize
إلى جانب 14 بيضةً غير مخصبة
and will blow up.
وستنفجر.
They'll be infected with bacteria, they will explode
ستغزوها الجراثيم وتنفجر
and those bacteria will threaten the life of this one embryo
وستهدد هذه الجراثيم حياة هذا الجنين
that has a chance.
الذي يملك فرصة في الحياة.
We don't know if it was our handling methods that went wrong
لا ندري إن كنا قد أخطأنا في أساليبنا
and we don't know
ونحن لا نعلم
if it was just this coral on this reef, always suffering from low fertility.
إذا كان المرجان في هذه الشعاب فقط هو الذي يعاني من قلة الخصوبة.
Whatever the cause,
مهما كان السبب،
we have much more work to do before we can use baby corals
لدينا الكثير من العمل قبل أن نتمكن من استعمال صغار المرجان
to grow or fix or, yes, maybe save coral reefs.
لتنمية أو ترميم أو ربما إنقاذ الشعاب المرجانية.
So never mind that they're worth hundreds of billions of dollars.
إذًا لا تبال بفكرة أنها تساوي بلايين الدولارات.
Coral reefs are hardworking animals and plants and microbes and fungi.
إن الشعاب المرجانية هي حيوانات ونباتات وأحياء دقيقة وفطر يات مجتهدة.
They're providing us with art and food and medicine.
تمدنا بالجمال والطعام والدواء.
And we almost took out an entire generation of corals.
رغم أننا تقريبًا قضينا على جيل كامل منها،
But a few made it anyway, despite our best efforts,
لكن نجا القليل منها رغم مجهوداتنا،
and now it's time for us to thank them for the work they did
والآن حان الوقت لنرد لها الدين،
and give them every chance they have to raise the coral reefs of the future,
ونمنحها فرصة لتنمية جيل جديد من الشعاب المرجانية.
their coral babies.
جيلاً من صغار المرجان.
Thank you so much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)